you need to watch this video if you want to stop losing trades pointlessly I'm going to teach you about closures why they're important and how you can actually use them to validate trades avoid losses and make big wins so let's not waste any time we'll get straight into it now so first things first what is a closure well if we're looking at a 1 hour chart here let's imagine these candles are hourly candles that means every hour that passes a candle will form and at the end of the hour and the
start of the new hour the candle will close so for example this would be our closure this would take place at the start of a new hour this would be the open price of the next candle at the end of that hour once again we get a closure and this continues we get a closure and open at the start of each hour so a candle closure is just where the candle is when the new candle opens in this instance the closure is here the closure is then there there there there there there and then all the way up there okay
now the reason we need to wait for these closures is because until a candle closes it can reverse on itself now if we take a look at this instance we're in an uptrend in this example the Market's uptrending we formed a high the market then came down formed a higher low now the Market's pushing up to form this potential higher high if the market was able to close over this swing high that would open doors to continued uptrending movements meaning we could continue buying this Market because we know it's
going up because it's continuing to make new higher Highs but if the market does not close above and instead the market does this and pulls back down before that hourly candle closes if it close down here then this would actually be a rejection of the high cuz when we're looking at candles we have the bodies and we have the Wicks the body is this large block area the wick are these sticks that we get on top or below candles Wicks show attempted prices within a given time frame so in this
instance this Wick shows us that the market attempted to go this high but actually got rejected and the closure ended up being here now this means that the only confirmed price action within this price range is between this low the open price and this High the closure price anything above that was just attempted price also known as rejected price so this is rejected price action and then this is confirmed price action just here now what does this show well this shows the confirmation has actually
confirmed lower than the previous swing High and the only push above that had was a wick which was rejected so this Market attempted to push higher but failed to close above which actually rejects entirely the concept of seeing closures and continuations above this level and instead suggests that maybe we could move even lower because we haven't closed above the high so we've rejected a new high maybe indicating that we could be ready to turn into a downtrend now if you saw this candle while it was
open and it's moving up and down and you decide to buy this candle before it closes cuz you think that it's closing above the swing High well if the candle then pushes all the way back down here you've bought on unconfirmed price action you've actually bought into a rejection of higher prices which means the likelihood of your trade working out and not instead doing this is now considerably lower and it's likely this trade could reverse on you so if you bought up here during this push up you
had your stop loss here well then it's very possible the market could even sink and stop you out of your trade without actually playing off at all if you for the next hourly candle to open so you wait for a closure and the next hourly candle opens like this for example well now you have that confirmation so the likelihood of us continuing even higher is actually now pretty much set in stone and a lot more likely because the market has proven to us that it's ready to make new highs so that's why we need to wait
for closures because if we don't get a closure and instead we get a wick well then it's likely that the market will flip on us or at least the probability of the market flipping on us is a lot stronger than it would have previously been which means you can get caught up buying against movements like this that could instead actually lead us into a new downtrend so following on from that if the swing high was rejected telling us not to get into a Buy trade and then the market moved lower and pushed past
the previous swing low well this could potentially open the doors to trading the other way which could completely flip our bias and if we were aware of this and we waited for confirmations we'd be able to take advantage of this new bearish price action but what could also happen is actually we go and reject the low as well so taking a look down here let's say we pushed down initially we formulated some bearish price action but then before the candle closed we had a push back up like this and then we
closed as a bullish candle once again well now we are seeing the same thing again we're seeing a rejection of this swing low this is basically showing an area where sellers were pushing the market down but at some point down here buyers took massive control of this market and ended up running it back up to close at this point if following on from this point we then had a bullish candle that managed to go up and close above that previous swing high so we'd be looking around this point here well this would then validate
the buyers finally okay because what we've actually shown is an attempt to go higher that failed then we had an attempt to go lower which massively failed followed by an attempt to go higher which succeeded with this closure and if this candle was to close up here then we could continue with our bullish ideas potentially looking to buy on pullbacks to take this Market higher so really we have to wait for closures because you've seen just how Dynamic this Market has been and in this example
I've just showed you how you could have been tricked twice if you hadn't waited for candles to close first at this top point up here when the market rejected the high and second when the market rejected this low now obviously this can be a big back and forth which can be hard to get your head around but really it can all be solved by just waiting for the candle closures like this that we see here cuz if we wait for a closure above or below a swing point then we have the confirmation we need to
understand whether a market is building strength in one way or the other in a meaningful manner so whichever time frame you're looking at whether it's the 1 hour or the 4 Hour or the one day or the one minute it really doesn't matter you just need to always wait for those candle closures to occur when you get a closure like this above or below a swing point you are ready to go with your trades but if you get rejections like this one and this one here then you should just wait out of the market until
the market tells you to make a move let's take a look at an example of this then this is a market that we've started to see pushing up in some bullish price action okay we're getting some higher highs and higher lows forming from an internal structure perspective now if we zoom out we can see that overall this is a downtrending market right so the larger picture is bearish and then this smaller picture is bullish where we're currently getting these higher highs and higher lows now we can see what we've
got here is pretty much a little swing high so what we could expect to see would be if the market was able to close Above This high that could potentially lead us into some new uptrending moves right so from supply and demand perspective let's say we wanted to look at possibly buying from this area if the market is able to close above the high that it is currently trading at so if we were to close where we are we may anticipate that the market could pull back towards demand and then continue
buying this could be the indication that maybe the market is starting to shift CU we have seen that this High here is actually now being broken so that point point just there could be seeing a change in the trend right we could be starting to see these buyers take control now this is then the point where we want to make sure we are getting closures Above This level right above this swing high if the market is able to close above that will give us what we need in terms of confirmation to continue trading higher but if the
market fails to close above then we could instead be potentially about to see continuations lower in this market because it will show us that the swing High has been rejected so a rejection would be no closure and then a confirmation would be closure Above This would leave us with two scenarios well the first scenario would be if we get the rejection we would start instead looking for a sell so rejection would potentially open doors to cells if the market is able to close and give us the confirmation that
would give us what we need in order to focus on a buy right so confirmation above meaning if we just ended the hour exactly where we are now that would be confirmation for us to buy this Market if we reject and we close beneath well then that would be a rejection that's not a confirmation that's not a closure the closure failed we've actually just seen rejected price action up there which means instead we could look for a sell okay so let's take a look at how this plays out then if we allow this
candle to close and the next one to open we see that we've actually closed with a rejection here right so we got that rejection scenario that we're talking about this is the point where the candle closed and a new one opened the next candle has been slightly bullish so far with some rejections but nothing is really locked in just yet we need to see how this Market is going to move now here we've seen a little push down in the market so we're starting to see a kind of rejection that we might want to
see and now we've seen a little push under the previous structural low now that we've started to see this market closing a little bit lower we could potentially be opening the doors here to take those shorts that we wanted to see now obviously we're looking to see if there's going to be significant rejection again cuz remember if we saw significant rejections we could actually just see the market go and close back Above This high and continue which is why we always want to make sure we're
looking at closures now because this area failed to close we can pretty much eliminate that demand Zone and instead realistically targets wise we would be looking at taking this Market back down towards some previous swing lows right we've seen a failure to trade higher which means therefore we could potentially see opportunity to trade lower okay so watching this market we've seen some closures beneath just here we saw a closure under this level initially we've then seen the market push down
we'd now be looking to see if we can again close beneath that level and as we have here we would now be looking at opportunities to sell this Market if we were able to pull back so for example the setup we could look at would be something like this we could sell there we could have stops above the zone and targets wise we could trade this down into one of those areas of supply right so allowing this Market to play out you see there we got the pullback tap into Supply now the market is pushing down
tackling those swing lows so that's a good thing that's what we want to see now we've seen as well there has been a closure under this first level and now that we've approached this second level what do we get we got a closure so let's just zoom in on that real quick you can see just down here the level of which we took profits on that first trade we have a closure what does this tell us well this tells us we can go lower if we'd have rejected this level with a wick and pushed back up that would be grounds to
potentially trade it back the other way right we would be saying okay maybe the market is not ready to close beneath maybe we're seeing rejections so therefore we could potentially see this Market return to the highs but because we've had this closure just here we could now anticipate that any pullbacks would provide us with pretty much selling opportunities once again now for this what I'm going to do is drop down to a 30 minute time frame see if we have any refined areas which are un retested
we've got this Supply at the top now if you want to watch a video on supply and demand click the uh card at the top of the video just now I'll also put a link in the description but at this point we have Supply Zone which could potentially be traded into we have closures telling us this Market is going lower the reason I would use this for entry is due to something called imbalance again there will be a lesson in the description and because we have the closures we're now looking for continued downside so if the
Market's able to pull back we could look for a sell this sell could continue down for this trade let's just keep it simple and look at this open demand Zone below so our trade would look something a little bit like this that would be the position that we could look to take and that would provide us with opportunity to trade this Market lower now that we've had closures so let's see how this goes if we run it through we got closure second closure which is good we have a wick here but
the market did already close beneath so that is a good sign it's pretty much what we want to see to confirm the downside if we have closure closure then Wick don't worry about that Wick too much cuz the closures have already happened right then we traded back to supply we hit the supply Zone we got triggered into the position at this point here as of right now the trade is still going we haven't swept this High which is where our stop loss would be and then you can see that the market has
made a big drive to the downside to fill that Target continuing the downside price action as confirmed by the candle closures we got here we had the closures initially under this level opening the doors to shorts then we had the closures underneath this level opening the doors to continue shorts once the market pulled back I want to bring attention however to this area here because here on the 30 minute we can see the market did actually close right this level here was closed above on the 30 minute so
although the hourly rejected couldn't we get tricked into the market from here well what I want to talk about is time frame relevance now you remember we set this trade up we did our initial setup analysis on the 1 hour time frame right so the hourly was the initial time frame now we are operating on the 30 minute time frame following on from what we saw on the hourly we're using that 30 minute if you remember simply to get the more refined Supply zones or areas to get into trades from such as what we've
covered here but the setup premise was built on the hourly so let's go to the hourly you'll see the swing high that we initially looked at didn't close above right we had rejections up there bringing the market back down and truly opening those doors to that continued downside that we've seen the hourly being the most important time frame because this is where our setup came from take a look down here where we saw those closures previous L these still occurred these were confirmed on the 1
hour time frame which is our setup premise time frame our main time frame as well as this closure here that we saw underneath this structure this is also clear and visible on the hourly there is no rejection so when I talk about time frame relevance i' just say when you find a setup use that time frame to confirm that setup right this hourly setup was idea to buy if we closed above sell if we closed below so we want to make sure that we're looking at hourly closures or rejections this here again
was an hourly premise setup it was a potential buy if we close above sell if we close Below on the hourly time frame so although the 30 minute did actually close below as well we used the 30 minute to find the refined area we only trust the setup because the hourly the actual setup premise time frame closed beneath that level where we wanted it to close all right so make sure you're keeping things time frame relevant if you're seeing an hourly swing point and a 5minute candle rejects don't worry
about that too much because you might get another 5in minute candle that ends up closing the hourly bullish but if you see an area like this where the hourly failed to close above but a lower time frame did close above trust the higher time frame because that is where you found your setup that is what's going to be most accurate so remember always wait for closures before you get into any positions because these things validate whether a trade is actually viable or not and it's going to save you a hell of
a lot of money on pointless losses and also help you to trade with more confidence on the positions that have validated now if you want to learn how to build this into a trading system I have a free course called seven steps to profitable trades which is going to teach you exactly how to build validate and test a trading strategy so that you can become a profitable Trader with the information I've taught you today hit the top Link in the description to check that out and if you don't want to do
that then just check out this video that's going to teach you more about Market structure and liquidity Concepts and with that said and done that is all from me in this video so thank you for watching and I'll see you in the next one