Supply and demand is an incredible concept. But just like any other concept in trading, sometimes it fails. Fortunately, with supply and demand, a failure can actually provide a whole new opportunity. And there's even a way to see them coming before they happen. I'm going to be teaching you all about supply and demand fails, how to spot them early, and how to trade them successfully. Let's get to it. So, if you're new to the concept of supply and demand, or you kind of understand it,
but you don't really understand the theory behind it, we're going to break that down now. Supply and demand refers to price areas in a market where significant buying or selling has taken place. Now, this is what we call a demand zone. It's a little box that we can draw on the chart. And what this demand zone shows is an area where significant buying has entered the market. This impulse shows clear buying control from this level up to where the market is now. We know it shows clear buying control because there are these
large bullish candles and not really too much in the way of seller or bearish strength. So this shows a very strong push from buyers. Now the demand zone is the area just before this impulsive move. What a demand zone shows is the area where all of this buying began. Now, in the flip example where we'd be looking at a supply zone, it's simply the same, but instead we're looking at an area where supply is stepping into the market. So, lots more units being sold in. When we see a area before a
large downward move, this shows us that this area of consolidation, this sideways move, this is where the selling has kicked in. So, therefore, this is a premium price to sell your assets. If the market gets back to it, we'd be looking for other traders to sell assets at this level either through uh obligatory buyback later contracts like short positions or just through profit taking as well. So supply and demand essentially shows prices that buyers and sellers are happy to pay for assets. And
what we're looking for is a follow-through of that willingness to buy at these levels once the market returns to them. It's very simple stuff. So that's the theory behind supply and demand. The next thing we need to cover is just how we draw these zones. And this one's really quick. For me, I use the last candle before the impulse. So, in this example, we can see this is a indecision candle. There's wicks, tiny candle body. No real movement has been made throughout that candle. But the
next candle is a very large impulsive candle with clear buying control. The candle body is large. It's made a significant movement one way. That is the impulse candle. So, the last candle before the impulse is going to be the one we have marked on here. Now in a selling example again it would just simply be the final consolidation candle before the large downward move that becomes the supply. The reason I look at it like this is because this is the final exact point before major distribution took place. Okay. So that's
how I mark them. The last candle before the impulse. Now like all concepts in trading these supply and demand zones are sometimes just going to fail. They're not going to work. They're not going to hold. This example we have a demand zone here. we have another demand zone which is far beneath all the way down here. Now, this is the last candle before the impulse that still has imbalance into it. So, if we're looking for a reversal, we're going to be looking for that around this point.
Sometimes, as I've said, these zones simply will not hold. And if we run this market forward, you'll see that the market has pushed through this low. Now, what this does is creates what we call a demand fail, which is coming in around this point. And this gives us an indication that this market could potentially be ready to go lower. So this is where demand and supply fails actually become valuable to us. Rather than just losing a trade and not having any other opportunity, what we have here
is possibility to now say, well, if this demand hasn't worked, we haven't seen the buying pressure we wanted to see come in here. Now, we may go lower towards the next demand, which allows us to then potentially look for short opportunities down to this point because this demand failing and the ability to push lower that we've seen in the market is showing seller control coming in. So, we could look for pullbacks to higher areas of supply. We have two core ones in this range. This one here and this
one here. And we may see this as potential to sell down into the area of demand given that we've seen this first demand fail. the next logical kind of magnet point for the market to get to and then potentially react from is going to be the lower demand zone down here. Okay, so that's something we can actually utilize, take advantage of, and potentially find opportunities from. Now, you'll see this market ran all the way up, not reacting to the first zone, but filling the second zone, which could
potentially provide a trade in itself. Now just as a hypothetical position you can see that by selling from here we may have then grounds to take the market down to the next zone. Right? So what we can actually do when it comes to supply and demand failing is find somewhat shorterterm opportunities against the initial direction we were looking for. When we first came in to this demand, we would have been looking for a reversal to take this market higher. But given that it failed, we then see, okay,
buyers evidently are no longer in control in the way that we thought they were. What that is likely to do is see seller control continue until we meet another high interest area. The next high interest area will be the next area of demand. And as we see, when the market pulls back and hits a supply zone, we then get grounds to sell from there and target the next magnet point. So you can see we actually find opportunity within supply and demand fails. If a demand doesn't work, it then tells us, okay, we're no longer looking
at buyer control, we're looking at seller control. And then when we see that break, we can find opportunity to sell and use these next demand zones or swing lows or we'll look at a couple different examples as our targets for potential short-term sell trades against the overall direction that we initially looked for from demand. So supply and demand fails can actually be very valuable because yes, while they invalidate the first initial trade we were looking for, they provide us with these secondary opportunities. We can
flip the bias for the medium-term and look for trades like this one. And when we reach this area, that's where we can start looking the other way once again. All right, let's take a look at that example of that demand fail format in action. So let's say we see this market trading to the upside. We've seen it sweep beneath these relative equal lows just here. And we're looking to buy. We want to take a buy on this market. So, we're going to look at the last candle before the impulse. And we're going to
use this as our demand area to buy from. So, we may be looking for the market to make a little shift to the upside to validate. Well, in this case, it's going to be around this structural point to validate a new high so that we can join this trend. So, our current idea is to look for a push higher and then buy on the pullback like this. That is a good way to set up a trade. But if we see the market come down, fail to provide this break up and actually break to the downside, well, what this does is
actually just continues the downward price action that we're currently seeing here. And by failing at this demand, not only do we invalidate the buy, so we manage to get away with no trade here instead of a loss, we actually lead into possible sells because if we think about what demand shows, it's that large push of buying from this price level. So therefore, we see this price area as the discounted price to buy from. But when the market doesn't react there, it tells us that traders are not feeling that
anymore. We're not seeing institutional participants come in with that willingness to buy that they had previously. So what we can actually do is then look for possibility to trade down towards new areas of demand. Now if we look at these areas here, these have all been retested. Every time we create demand, the wick has come back and retested it. So these are not areas we'd be expecting to see a reversal again cuz areas that have already been hit, a demand zone that's already been tapped
is not a demand zone we want to look at. Now, there's more context around that thought in a little bit when we look at how to forecast demand breaks or demand fails before they occur. But for now, the next open demand, the next point with any imbalance is going to be the demand right down here that we call this the extreme demand cuz it's the furthest in the price movement. It's the lowest possible one. So now we have the understanding that given that we've broken through this demand, we are
likely to continue trading lower towards the next demand. The demand here has failed. There's no meaningful points between where we are right now and this lower demand where we're likely to see a new influx of buying. Now, when we consider this demand down here, we know this was seen as a discounted price to buy from. Okay, hence the impulsive move that took place after this small consolidation. Therefore, if we are going to see another influx of buying, it's likely to take place from here,
which pretty much leaves an open range from where we are now all the way down there, where there isn't really any push back from buyers. So, what we could actually do here is look at selling the existing supply that we've come into and we could target that demand zone for a trade. So an idea of a position could be something like this where what we're actually doing is taking advantage of the fact this demand has failed to hold and now instead we're looking to continue selling in line with what is
currently on this more refined view the predominant trend which is down and then we would look to take the market down to this demand get out and that is where we could look for the next possible buys or if we don't get a buy from there and we get a demand fail well simply we can look to the left and take a look at lower price areas which in this chart we have quite a ways down to identify the next possible point that the market could lead into. So we treat these supply and demand zones as kind of
levels for flips, right? Yes, we initially want to buy from there because we are moving with this larger uptrend. But when we see there is no reaction from it and when we see the market breaking down instead, well, that opens doors to very clear possibility for us to use this as a pretty much forecast or prediction that the market is now likely to go lower. If the market was going to go higher, it would have done so by reacting from demand. But because we didn't see a reaction from demand, and
because we've now broken lower, we can continue moving with that overall market flow, that overall direction, and finalize that move to the next demand. And that would be how we trade supply and demand fails. So you don't only have to rely on demand zones to provide the confirmation you want for buy trades, but you can also look at them as a way of providing confirmation if the market melts down instead. Right now, let's take a look at an example the other way with a supply fail. What we've got here
is a market that is moving to the downside, creating lower lows and lower highs. Our next selling point if we wanted to sell into this market would be from this supply zone just here which is going to be the supply zone that's just above price. So a selling move could look like this. However, you see the market comes through and then actually breaks above this supply zone which actually then creates a supply fail here. This supply has now failed. Now our next movement would then be to look for imbalances and the next area of
potential supply that the market could react from. We have imbalance that leads all the way up. Potential supply there, but we've got equal high liquidity. These 1 2 3 4 points there, which means we wouldn't look at this supply. We would instead look at least at the supply zone just above. So our next potential supply for reversals if this market is going to go bearish is going to be there. Essentially, by creating this high and creating this supply fail, we've opened the doors to at least
trading through this range into this area here before we then get any further sell-offs if that is what we do. So, we create a situation where now we can say, okay, the safe thing to do, the obvious thing to do is going to be buying from this area of demand because the market has somewhat shifted, even if it is inside of an internal range. And then when we get into here, we can assess that for reversals and either go short or if we again break through. Well, then we have continued buying potential
through to the next supply. Okay, these points here. So, what our trade would look like then given that we've created a supply fail would be to identify the demand zone, which would be in this case here just beneath the market gap. A gap and an imbalance essentially are showing the same thing. A gap though is just a little bit stronger. When we see a gap, it's highly likely to be filled. So, we would place our buy there with our stops beneath the zone and the targets could easily go up to here. And this is a
situation where a supply fail, basically a supply zone failing to hold and take the market lower actually opens doors to a pretty immediate buying opportunity. As you can see, that follows through to a profitable outcome trade. So, again, this example flipped the other way. This time, we're not looking at demand fails. We're looking at supply fails. But all we see is a zone that could potentially cap price breaking which opens doors to trading the other way. Basically range to range through to the next point of
potential supply. And that movement alone provides us with a trade which in this case could have brought back 4% or a little bit more in a very simple format of just finalizing a buy into the next supply before we then await the next actions from the market. Now, earlier on, I explained to you that you can actually start to see demand and supply fails before they've taken place, which can be useful because it allows you to catch early trades or it at least lets you see where the market is likely
to go next to avoid taking trades in the wrong direction and also set yourselves up ahead of time so that you're ready to pounce on the move. To explain the auction theory in a quick sense, just as a recap, we say that if we have a demand zone like this with a large impulsive buying move after it, it shows us that the price range between here and here is seen as a discount price for this asset. So based on that theory, we expect if the market gets back to this level again, there's likely to be a good
influx of buying to take us into a new high. That would be the demand zone reacting as expected. So given that we are generally expecting fast movements to take place meaning we may get one tap into this demand zone and then a continuation higher. Now if you take a look at what happened in this zone we actually created the first tap then we pushed up. We came back down for a second tap and then we come back in again for a third tap. Now what is this telling us about this demand zone? Well, by coming back in for a second and third
tap, we're seeing that the buying pressure that's coming in from this level is nowhere near as strong as it used to be. When we saw the buying pressure coming in from this level when the zone was created, we saw a direct push to the upside, a direct impulse driving us into new highs. This time though, we failed to get away and the markets returned again. We've attempted and failed to get away. So this is now three taps, three attempts to go higher and every single time up till now we
have failed which shows us that the buying pressure inside of this range is not strong. Okay, we don't have strong buying pressure. So what can that tell us then? Well, it tells us this demand is no longer seen as a discount by as many traders in as much force as it previously was. Therefore, it gives us insight into the fact that this market may potentially go lower. So there's a few ways we could set up here. The first off is the more aggressive stance would be to look for direct possibility to
sell down through the break. So you could in an aggressive sense depending on kind of how you trade look at a trade from a supply zone to take us through the demand and then into wherever we wanted to go. That would be the first and the most aggressive way to trade. The second way to trade would be once the demand fail actually comes through. Then you can start looking at areas of supply for the market to react from and you could potentially look at selling down once those reactions have come through. Right? So if we followed that
through to where we are right now, we see the demand officially failed in and around this level. We then got a pull back in to that area of supply and as of the time of right now recording this video, the market is on its way down towards these lows. So there's two potential trading opportunities. Number one is aggressive. After the third tap in, we start looking at opportunity to sell down into the lows of the demand fail. Following that, the less aggressive stances. Once the demand fail actually comes through, we immediately
position ourselves into shorts to bring this market lower. both sides of this, whichever way we're looking at it is actually just basically identifying this demand is very likely to go given that it is being hit multiple times and therefore positioning ourselves to profit from when this market actually does drive through demand. When the demand fail becomes reality and the market starts trading lower. Now, this then opens doors to targeting lower zones. As we've said, the lowest zone in
this market that we would then generally look at as a target would be the area of demand just here. This is going to be the next demand. There's no real demand zone inside of here. They've all been retested by wicks. Therefore, seeing one, two, three pushes into this low. Gives us an insight that we can look for selling potential to take us from this existing range down towards the next meaningful point of demand. Right? So, the clearest way to identify supply and demand fails before they occur is going
to be seeing multiple retests of the same demand. Think of it like a wall. And every time the market hits this wall, it's hitting it with a hammer. If we hit it once and bounce away, that's great. But if we hit it a second time, it's getting weaker. It will start to crumble. We come in a third time and now this wall is incredibly weak. Eventually, it's going to break. If the market, if the hammer keeps dropping on this level, on this wall, it's going to break eventually, which will lead us
through to lower prices, which is where we manage to profit by, of course, joining this and understanding that direction either before or at the earliest possible stages of this break taking place. All right, so here's a potential opportunity on GBP JPY. We started to see the market breaking lower from this high up here. We had a supply zone retested, sell-off, creation of a new supply zone, and now we've come in and retested this. Now, if we let this market run forward, of course, what we
would ideally want to see would be a big run lower to create a new bearish impulse. Given it some time, we do get a nice trade to the downside. We fail to make a new low, though, and then we actually come in for a second tap. Now again from what we've just discussed this makes this zone weaker cuz every time the market comes and hits this zone again we are seeing that the sellers in here and in here and now in here are not coming in in as much force as they were back here where we managed to create an
impulsive move to the downside. As you can see as well this push has created a closure very high to the top of the zone which tells us that buyers at this point are stronger than they've been at any point through this supply. If you think about where this bullish candle closed, that shows buyers have managed to get the market up here with some sustainability, which they never managed to do at any of these previous points. That shows again buyer control, really pushing against this supply. So, this is
a supply zone that actually becomes better as a buying opportunity now than a selling opportunity. We're in a position where we've created demand here, pushed away, pulled back. We could happily look at buying the market from this point and looking to take it higher. I mean, realistically in this kind of market, we would just want to take it towards the next open point of supply like this. So, you'd work inside of the current trading range of where we've come into basically this larger
unrefined area of demand. You'd look inside of there for your refined opportunity to buy this market up towards that high. Right? This one would be, I would say, less aggressive. Although we don't actually have the full supply fail yet, this is as good as seeing that when we have a bullish closure that is so high to the top of a supply zone. In fact, the highest we've seen throughout the entire duration of the supply zone failures to go lower and multiple pushes into that area of supply, building strength every time.
That's a very high probability chance then that we're actually likely to end up breaking above. When we've broken above, we can again look at continuation possibility from areas of demand. Basically refining again inside of this price action and looking to buy once the market returns to that level to take us up to, of course, as we've said, next points of open supply. So when we see multiple taps into a supply, okay, one, two, three, we're seeing continued weakness here, which is therefore likely
to lead into continuations to the upside rather than the good strong sell to the downside, which of course is a little bit crazy because when we see supply, we generally expect to sell that. But this is a very clear sign when we see these market levels hit multiple times. Essentially, just think of the context of what this is truly showing you, which is showing you selling pressure is not so strong. Buying pressure is actually building up against this level. Therefore, our supply zone that we initially thought was good may actually
be better as a flip into some buys. So, to sum up, demand and supply fails in a nutshell. Demand zones are areas of significant buying power. And what we're looking for is a reaction and continuation to the upside. If we don't see that given an immediate break, for example, we would then use this demand fail as an opportunity to sell down towards lower points of demand or other target areas. Now, if we do see an initial reaction, but it doesn't manage to make much ground in the market, and
we see multiple taps coming back in to this same level, every one of these taps weakens the zone and gives us an insight that the next likely movement could be a downward move, which allows us to sell early into the move as we start to see this zone being hit multiple times, or just gives us insight that this is likely to go and allows us to prime setups that are ready to be executed if we see that first demand fail. The same exact format is true for supply zones. If we see supply zone fails, that leads
into trades higher into higher areas of supply. And if we see a supply zone hit multiple times, well, that opens the doors to an understanding that the next likely move is going to be a buy, not a sell.